<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>feed</title>
    <link href="https://roadtransport.news/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://roadtransport.news" />
    <updated>2021-03-04T17:12:05+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://roadtransport.news</id>

    <entry>
        <title>To Insure Or Self-insure?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/to-insure-or-self-insure/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/to-insure-or-self-insure/</id>
            <category term="Insurance"/>

        <updated>2021-03-04T17:12:05+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/27/To-insure-or-self-insure.jpg" alt="truck insurance " />
                    Fleet insurance is essential for businesses with vehicle fleets and drivers. With proper management and meticulousness, fleet managers can reduce insurance costs, improve the safety of employees and benefit from&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/27/To-insure-or-self-insure.jpg" alt="truck insurance " />
                <p><strong>Fleet insurance is essential for businesses with vehicle fleets and drivers. </strong></p>
<p>With proper management and meticulousness, fleet managers can reduce insurance costs, improve the safety of employees and benefit from as much insurance cover as is required.</p>
<p>But with escalating insurance costs, many fleet managers, particularly those overseeing large fleets, are opting to partially cover their vehicles and even opting to self-insure.</p>
<p>Insurance is an expensive mechanism to protect losses.</p>
<p>Insurance premiums comprise broker commission, administration costs, costs associated with collecting funds (for large claims) and profit.</p>
<p>So, what would be a R100 claim, for instance, can easily end up costing R140.</p>
<p>For this reason, it is important to consider whether you should be insuring or self-insuring all of your risks.</p>
<p>From truck insurance for SMEs to comprehensive insurance for large logistics businesses with substantial fleets, there are flexible, commercial vehicle insurance options suitable for the requirements for any company.</p>
<p>If you operate in the <a href="https://roadtransport.news/tags/logistics/">logistics</a> industry, then it makes sense to take out commercial vehicle <a href="https://roadtransport.news/tags/insurance/">insurance </a>with expansive territorial limits and goods-in-transit cover included.</p>
<p>In this way you are covered if something should happen to your vehicle, driver and/or cargo at the <a href="https://roadtransport.news/tags/cross-border-trucking/">border post</a> or in a foreign country.</p>
<p>Similarly, if you run a shuttle service, you may want to consider taxi insurance and supplement it with fleet insurance.</p>
<p>Taxi insurance includes liability cover, which ticks the box of covering the risk of personal injury and even death when transporting people.</p>
<p>However, some risks don’t warrant the cost, time and effort involved with high excesses and claiming from an insurer.</p>
<p>If you have a stable fleet, reliable drivers and can accurately predict the associated fleet costs, then you could take a particular risk upon yourself or even outsource a portion of the risk to an insurer.</p>
<p>One of the more obvious risks that fleet operators can consider taking on, is windscreen cover. Accurate, historical stats can provide insights into the frequency and severity of windscreen claims.</p>
<p>Armed with these insights, a simple calculation is all it takes to determine whether the sum of premiums and excesses are more or less than the cost of paying for the replacements out of your own funds.</p>
<p>By self-insuring windscreens, fleet operators will be motivated to negotiate the best deals from windscreen suppliers, thereby bringing down the average cost of repair.</p>
<p>Fleet operators will also take risk mitigation actions, such as ensuring that all rules are followed according to the fleet vehicle policy, to minimise the occurrence of these incidents.</p>
<p>The bigger one’s fleet, the more financial sense it makes to self-insure against windscreen losses.</p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="https://roadtransport.news/four-causes-of-truck-rollovers/">The Four Causes of Truck Rollovers</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Africa Needn&#x27;t Use Inferior Engine Oil</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/africa-shouldnt-accept-inferior-oils/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/africa-shouldnt-accept-inferior-oils/</id>
            <category term="Opinion"/>

        <updated>2021-03-02T20:18:35+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/26/Renault-truck-in-Algeria.jpg" alt="old heavy truck driving in Algeria" />
                    Cost and quality matters in the oil and lubricant sectors worldwide, and even more so in Africa. It is all good and well bringing quality to the continent, but high&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/26/Renault-truck-in-Algeria.jpg" alt="old heavy truck driving in Algeria" />
                <p><strong>Cost and quality matters in the oil and lubricant sectors worldwide, and even more so in Africa.</strong></p>
<p>It is all good and well bringing quality to the continent, but high pricing in the African context excludes the majority except the well-to-do businesses and elite role players.</p>
<p>Consequently, most market participants are forced to use inferior product.</p>
<p>As a business, we are moving trucks throughout various countries on the continent at any given point, interacting with local businesses and various supply chains, and we have observed that Africa is modernising at a noticeable pace.</p>
<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://roadtransport.news/cross-border-trucking-remains-dire/">Cross-border Trucking Remains Dire</a></p>
<p>In the oil sector, Africa has traditionally used older vehicles which utilised certain mineral oil products, but an increase in the standard of living across borders has led to the introduction of a modernised commercial fleet and private vehicle market.</p>
<p>This has necessitated bringing in modern, high-spec oils to the continent, but with the proviso that these still be affordable.</p>
<p>Despite the increase in economic activity, on a like-for-like basis, the buying power on the continent broadly does not match that of developed markets.</p>
<p>That’s the key.</p>
<p>Africa deserves quality at a more palatable price point, and this is achieved by streamlining operations, and carefully managing supply chains.</p>
<p>This, in turn, stimulates business activity in various countries on the continent.</p>
<p>All these components – from quality, to price, to active downstream business opportunities – build trust in a brand.</p>
<p>So, what does a multinational need to do then, to switch the script and adapt to Africa as opposed to Africa needing to adapt to a model of business that originates in developed markets?</p>
<p>It sources the best base oil at a cost that doesn’t pass unnecessary financial burden onto Africans.</p>
<p>Then, when it comes to additives, it travels to the countries with best practise and negotiates deals that suit the African market.</p>
<p>It then invests in a manufacturing process that does not compromise on quality but is designed to pass the cost savings to the end-consumer.</p>
<p>It hires and outsources various aspects of the business to Africans.</p>
<p>It is our view that any oil company that wishes to adjust the status quo in favour of the people of this continent needs to demonstrate three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>It must understand the African context</li>
<li>It must be generating business on the continent and,</li>
<li>It must have a proven track record which speaks to credibility.</li>
</ol>
<p>Petrocam’s story in Nigeria is perhaps testament to this philosophy.</p>
<p>Entering a market dominated by truly colossal giants is not easy. Many have tried and many have failed.</p>
<p>However, with a client-centric approach focused on quality, reliability, and price sensitivity, Petrocam has been a steady supplier of refined products into Nigeria.</p>
<p>Today, with solar-powered filling stations around the country, Petrocam and its lubricants has been accepted as an African brand.</p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Petrocam Opens 7th Solar Powered Filling Station in Lagos, Nigeria</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ixNOmYuIBrA" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Africa’s time is now.</p>
<p>Sure, the pandemic and other geopolitical events have added challenges, but there is no denying the potential of this continent by the mere fact that <a href="https://www.citiesalliance.org/newsroom/news/cities-alliance-news/%C2%A0burgeoning-africa-youth-population-potential-or-challenge%C2%A0#:~:text=Almost%2060%25%20of%20Africa's%20population,a%20challenge%20for%20the%20continent." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">60% of this continent is under 25 years old.</a></p>
<p>Businesses that build their models in favour of this demographic today will enjoy a mutually beneficial relationship for many years to come.</p>
<p>What does any of this have to do with South Africa, the most developed market on the continent? South Africans deserve to be treated in the same way.</p>
<p>While there are glossy buildings and pockets of immense wealth, there are also large swathes of the population that are excluded from quality and durability on price point alone.</p>
<p>Beyond that, why should the wealthier pay more just because they can?</p>
<p>This is the pain point that Petrocam hopes to fill with its African experience: provide quality at a far more inclusive price.</p>
<p>By doing this, South Africans, like their African counterparts don’t have to settle for inferior quality because of cost.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Roaring Success for MAN Automotive</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/roaring-success-for-man-automotive/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/roaring-success-for-man-automotive/</id>
            <category term="OEM&#x27;s"/>

        <updated>2021-03-01T13:38:44+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/MAN-Automotive-TG2.jpg" alt="MAN TG2 truck" />
                    MAN Automotive South Africa had a phenomenal year in 2020 despite the well-documented challenges. The company is particularly proud of its net sales volumes from its premium TG product range,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/MAN-Automotive-TG2.jpg" alt="MAN TG2 truck" />
                <p><strong>MAN Automotive South Africa had a phenomenal year in 2020 despite the well-documented challenges. </strong></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The company is particularly proud of its net sales volumes from its premium TG product range, which enabled it to achieve its best extra-heavy truck market share since 2006. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">2020 also saw MAN Automotive's extra-heavy TGM, TGS and TGX models take the company onto the local sales podium. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Since 2014, MAN Automotive has risen from the number seven market position to the number three market position. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The company's EfficientLine on-highway and XHD on-off highway 6x4 truck tractors have led the way – proving both payload productivity and fuel-efficiency consistently – and often setting the benchmark for Total Cost of Ownership in those industry segments.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/P5.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-xs.JPG 300w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-sm.JPG 480w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-md.JPG 768w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P5-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="MAN TG2 front three-quarter" width="800" height="640"></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">From May 2020 onwards, MAN performed month-on-month better than in 2019 in both volume of used sales and used sales prices. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">It ended the year with the lowest stock level in years and healthy demand for its used vehicles.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Furthermore, the rental business more than doubled in size from 2019 to 2020. The manufacturer has also embarked on bus rentals with huge success. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Dealer Developments</strong></span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN Automotive has taken ownership of George, PE and East London to run these facilities as wholly-owned subsidiary territories rather than through private capital dealerships.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The manufacturer also undertook facility expansions at the Centurion and Pietermaritzburg sites. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Centurion now hosts the full MAN Training Academy, while Pietermaritzburg hosts the value-adding Truck Modification Centre.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Conservation Efforts</strong></span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The 54,000 sqm MAN Truck and Bus assembly plant is located in Pinetown, KwaZulu-Natal.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The plant was established in 1962 and is instrumental in assembling MAN Truck and Bus chassis for South Africa and the SAE region.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/P7.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-xs.JPG 300w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-sm.JPG 480w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-md.JPG 768w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P7-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="MAN TG2 interior RHD" width="800" height="534"></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN assembles different TGS and TGM models in the truck segment. These vehicles have different ratings based on customer needs and applications. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN also assembles both front and rear-engined bus chassis here as required. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The plant imports kits from Germany and Brazil and receives some local materials to complete the chassis. It is a very lean set up and has the capacity to make 14 chassis per shift. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">While being an operations plant, the MAN team works in different directions to support the environment and localization efforts.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The plant generates electricity through solar panels, which are installed on the roof. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Excess energy is fed back into the power grid. MAN Automotive has also started reducing the consumption of diesel to minimize pollution by shifting to electrical energy. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Water conservation and recycling is a routine activity. The focus here is on continuous improvement in all areas.   </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The plant has won awards at the international level for many years with good practices implemented. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The company also supports community development through Corporate Social Responsibility activity, assists some schools/families, and trains students to develop further.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Flexible Finance</strong></span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Covid-19 has severely impacted some transport operators and logistics service providers. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN and its financing arm, <a href="https://man-finance.co.za/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MAN Financial Services</a>, have supported many customers by refinancing their rolling assets over longer periods or restructuring their maintenance contracts.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">While the Rate of Exchange severely impacted the brand, it managed to help many customers with existing contract adjustments in the spirit of partnership.  </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Given the current economic climate, striving for the lowest possible total cost of ownership is now more relevant than ever before. </span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/P6.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-xs.JPG 300w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-sm.JPG 480w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-md.JPG 768w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/25/responsive/P6-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="MAN TG2 side view" width="800" height="640"></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN had to train its front-line staff to unpack all fixed and variable cost aspects much more transparently for its customers and hone every cost element to the most competitive position possible. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">This remains MAN's mission, and it continues to improve on every component of the cost calculation.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Entry-level requirements to be a serious player in heavy-duty trucking include: </span></p>
<ul>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Having the full package of truck specification hardware </span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Finance and funding instruments</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Various product warranties</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Repair and maintenance contracts</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Life asset management </span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Telematics and fleet management services</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">End-of-term guaranteed residual value linked to specific vehicle return conditions</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN says all of its front-line sales and support staff know and understand these offerings to a tee.  </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">This is crucial since communication and training bring a clear differentiating edge in the marketplace.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Bright Future</strong></span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">MAN will continue to move towards its vision of being the first choice in transportation for its customers. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">To ensure it keeps itself honest to this cause, it continues to embrace the strategic pillars which it deems enablers for success.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The company says it foresees that 2021 will be the most successful year ever for its current TG product range. </span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> The New MAN Truck Generation</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4CacbdSJsk0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">And, the latest generation of MAN trucks launched in Spain in 2020 will arrive in South Africa in late 2021. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Only a few minutes in the company of this totally re-designed vehicle makes it abundantly clear why MAN's TGX is the European Truck of the Year for 2021. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">With MAN customers rating it the best performing European OEM in the competitive Customer Satisfaction Index over the last half of 2020, the future looks bright for 2022 and beyond.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ctrack acquired by Convergence Partners</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/ctrack-acquired-by-convergence-partners/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/ctrack-acquired-by-convergence-partners/</id>
            <category term="Telematics"/>
            <category term="Press Release"/>

        <updated>2021-02-26T11:34:09+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/24/CTrack-4.jpg" alt="Ctrack SA control room" />
                    Ctrack South Africa will break away from Inseego following a purchase by investment management firm Convergence Partners. Convergence Partners will purchase the shares of the current South African entities. Inseego&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/24/CTrack-4.jpg" alt="Ctrack SA control room" />
                <p><strong>Ctrack South Africa will break away from Inseego following a purchase by investment management firm Convergence Partners. </strong></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Convergence Partners will purchase the shares of the current South African entities.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Inseego decided to divest Ctrack following a new demand on technology and Inseego’s 5G business, accelerated by the recent global pandemic. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">A strategy to focus on target markets that are closely aligned with their 5G business growth.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“We believe that this new partnership will bring a wealth of business knowledge and envisage many opportunities and positive synergies to benefit our business in general,” explains Hein Jordt, managing director of Ctrack SA.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“Our continued growth and success are what has enabled us to show favourable results, a motivator for Convergence Partners to invest during these times.” </span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Ctrack and Vehicle Tracking</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FyiRwj7uuCc" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The business will continue in its current form and retain the Ctrack brand name, which spans 30 years. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ctrack will continue to use their brand and related product names in the markets they serve.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">It will expand into new territories in Africa and the Middle East while developing world-class technologies for its customers.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“Our interest in the business relates to its proven market leader in the development of analytics solutions using big data extracted from the cloud platform,” says Mr Andile Ngcaba, chairman of Convergence Partners.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“We believe that our ownership of Ctrack will catalyze to enhance and accelerate its digital ambitions further,” Ngcaba concluded.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“Ctrack’s IOT and data analytics capabilities are a key component of an emerging sector in Africa and a good fit with our strategy of identifying high growth market players that build digital infrastructure in the continent,” adds Brandon Doyle, CEO of Convergence Partners.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“We believe our expertise can elevate the Ctrack business to new heights.” </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">“The management of Ctrack are confident this new partnership will open up a gateway of opportunities for the business. The company is better positioned to move forward and capture market opportunities,” concluded Jordt.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The transaction is subject to receipt of regulatory approvals and other closing conditions. It is expected to close during the second quarter of 2021.</span></p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/null">Telematics eases vaccine rollout</a></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cross-border Trucking Remains Dire</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/cross-border-trucking-remains-dire/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/cross-border-trucking-remains-dire/</id>
            <category term="Cross-Border Trucking"/>

        <updated>2021-02-21T16:43:15+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/23/Lebombo-Border-Trucks-Parked.jpg" alt="Trucks parked at Lebombo border" />
                    Long, snaking lines of trucks are a familiar sight at Southern African border posts. From non-standard procedures and processes between countries to a lack of information sharing, non-harmonisation and old-fashioned&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/23/Lebombo-Border-Trucks-Parked.jpg" alt="Trucks parked at Lebombo border" />
                <p><strong><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Long, snaking lines of trucks are a familiar sight at Southern African border posts.</span></strong></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">From non-standard procedures and processes between countries to a lack of information sharing, non-harmonisation and old-fashioned manual processes, the situation remains dire.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The lack of standard procedures, in particular, often results in chaos. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">At Chirundu, for instance, there is a fast-track lane on the Zambian side but not on the Zimbabwean side. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">While you can have trucks clearing on the Zambian side within an hour, it takes up to 15 hours in Zimbabwe, negating the whole process. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ideally, you would want to fast-track trucks on both sides.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Communication between country authorities is erratic. Many also opt to use paper systems rather than electronic solutions.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Infrastructure is another challenge we have as it is entirely inadequate for the traffic volumes. It is badly outdated and archaic in design. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Truck-weighing processes are cumbersome and slow, while corruption is rife.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Excessive charges worsen the situation and are slowly killing regional trade in the Southern African Development Community (SADC).</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Cross border permits serve no purpose and are nothing but another revenue collection tool, while there are a host of unnecessary permits, levies, taxes, and fees to be paid.</span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Trucks queue at the Chirundu Border Post</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wZvb5VamHcw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The Chirundu border post between Zambia and Zimbabwe is currently the only One-Stop Border Post (OSBP) in Southern Africa. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">But, it is not functioning well by all accounts because it faces the same challenges as the traditional border posts - high staff turnover, inadequate infrastructure, and poorly integrated customs systems.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">To bring about any change, we need total commitment and cooperation between heads of states. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Whether governments choose to implement OSBPs or smart borders, we need this done rapidly.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Infrastructure at border posts must also be upgraded to accommodate current and future traffic volumes.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Furthermore, there has to be a reduction in the number of weigh-bridge stations and police checkpoints along the transport corridors. Cross-border permits need scrapping.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The introduction of a yellow card or alternative insurance system recognised by all members and purchased in the country of origin would also improve the situation.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Just as important is introducing one cross-border charge or fee applicable in all member states.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Tata International Africa Introduces Five-year Warranty</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/tata-international-africa-introduces-five-year-warranty/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/tata-international-africa-introduces-five-year-warranty/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="OEM&#x27;s"/>

        <updated>2021-03-01T13:30:51+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Daewoo-Trucks.jpg" alt="Daewoo Trucks warranty" />
                    Tata International Africa has become the first company in Africa to introduce a standard warranty of five years on its entire Medium, Heavy and Extra Heavy Commercial Vehicle range. This&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Daewoo-Trucks.jpg" alt="Daewoo Trucks warranty" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Tata International Africa has become the first company in Africa to introduce a standard warranty of five years on its entire Medium, Heavy and Extra Heavy Commercial Vehicle range.</strong> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This first-of-its-kind Pan African five-year warranty applies to the full range of Tata Trucks and Buses as well as Daewoo Trucks in all 12 markets in which Tata International Africa operates.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Len Brand, CEO of Tata International Africa says the introduction of a five-year driveline warranty on the commercial vehicle range reinforces the company’s commitment to enhancing the customer ownership experience.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are extremely pleased to offer five-years of assurance on our range of commercial vehicles, while reiterating our commitment to the quality of our products,” says Brand. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Given Africa’s harsh and varied terrains, this new warranty goes a long way towards Tata International Africa’s pursuit of offering enhanced lifecycle benefits to its customers.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“So, whether a customer is in Kenya, Zambia or Ghana, or any other country in which we operate, they will have the same experience and benefits in terms of the warranty.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are customer obsessed and our Uptime strategy is bearing fruit.”</span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Daewoo Trucks in South Africa</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PPG7csCTnms" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Four years ago, we identified the components that we knew were imperative to the growth of our business. The final dream was to be the most sought-after distributor for commercial vehicles in Africa. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have been building towards that, with excellent work on improving the parts and service side of our business.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’ve worked equally hard on our network, expanding our footprint dramatically, especially in South Africa, where we have over 90 touchpoints.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’ve also added new products, working with our OEM partners, to ensure that we are able to provide products for specific niches.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The five-year warranty is applicable to all Tata and Daewoo commercial vehicles first registered on or after 1 January 2021. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is supported across Tata International Africa’s dealership and service network including over 450 touch point outlets and service facilities across the continent.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If a customer needs to sell the vehicle, they will enjoy a higher resale value and the warranty is transferable to the next owner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A warranty of such magnitude gives the customer assurance that the product is robust, reliable and durable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tata International Africa has also been successful in rolling out retail financing arrangements in six African markets.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Tata-Trucks.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-xs.jpg 300w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-sm.jpg 480w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-md.jpg 768w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Tata Trucks warranty" width="800" height="743"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We started this journey two years ago, and we’re thrilled to offer retail financing to our customers in so many African countries,” Brand continues. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Rest assured, six is not the end of this journey. We are planning to roll this out in all 12 countries in which we operate,” concluded Brand.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tata International Africa operates in South Africa, Ghana, Kenya, Ivory Coast, Malawi, Mozambique Nigeria, Senegal, Tanzania, Uganda, Zambia and Zimbabwe.</span></p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong>  <a href="https://roadtransport.news/cross-border-trucking-remains-dire/">Cross-border Trucking Remains Dire</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Four Causes Of Truck Rollovers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/four-causes-of-truck-rollovers/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/four-causes-of-truck-rollovers/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="Driver Training"/>

        <updated>2021-02-18T17:39:20+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/21/P32.jpg" alt="overturned truck" />
                    Truck rollovers can be devastating. Death or injuries to those involved, damages to property or roads, being responsible for the closure of a road for hours at a time and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/21/P32.jpg" alt="overturned truck" />
                <p><strong>Truck rollovers can be devastating. </strong></p>
<p>Death or injuries to those involved, damages to property or roads, being responsible for the closure of a road for hours at a time and the cost of repairs or replacement and the consequent downtime can leave a company millions out of pocket.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, there is seldom a week that photos of a rollover are not shared in the media.</p>
<p>The managing director of MasterDrive, Eugene Herbert, says with the right conditions a truck rollover happens easily.</p>
<p>“Trucks are prone to these kind of crashes as drivers have to contend with both a high centre of gravity and centrifugal forces that cause the truck to ‘lean’ in a curve or turn."</p>
<p>A number scenarios have high risk of rollovers.</p>
<p>"Four of these are particularly risky for truck drivers yet with the right training drivers can be prepared for what to expect and how to avoid this dangerous and costly position.”</p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Trucks Overturning Compilation</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hz4sNw6nSOg" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 1: Speed and cornering</strong></span></p>
<p>Speed is estimated to be the cause of up to 45% of crashes in corners and on highway onramps and offramps.</p>
<p>“When negotiating a corner, drivers need to use height, load and angle or configuration of the corner to decide what speed is required to safely navigate the corner,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 2: Incorrect loading</strong></span></p>
<p>The high centre of gravity requires the load to be secured. “If the load shifts during cornering the loss of balance increases rollover risk.</p>
<p>"Tankers can also be at increased risk when partially full as the sloshing of the liquid can upset the balance, particularly when cornering,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 3: Abrupt or oversteering </strong></span></p>
<p>Abrupt or sharp steering movements are risky. “The high centre of gravity will cause a truck to roll over if the driver abruptly steers around an obstacle."</p>
<p>"Drivers should also be cautious of oversteering in certain situations, such as when traction decreases."</p>
<p>"When traction is regained but oversteering continues, lateral force increases along with the risk of rollover,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 4: Driver error</strong></span></p>
<p>A study by international organisation FMSCA, suggests that 78% of tanker rollovers are due to driver error.</p>
<p>“This can be speeding in bad weather conditions, distracted driving, driving while on medication or while fatigued and various other dangerous driving habits.”</p>
<p>The difficulty with rollovers is that once the truck starts to tip, there is nothing you can do to stop it.</p>
<p>“Additionally, drivers may only feel the start of a rollover when it is well underway. This emphasises the importance of being aware of risk factors and what is required to ensure that you eliminate all the risks you can.</p>
<p>“MasterDrive’s rollover prevention training teaches drivers about risk factors and provides guidance on how to avoid falling victim to one."</p>
<p>"Importantly, the unique engineering of the truck allows drivers to feel what an actual rollover feels like without going all the way over.</p>
<p>"It is an invaluable opportunity to understand a rollover without the financial implications,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="https://roadtransport.news/insurance-and-driver-training-intertwined/">Insurance and driver training intertwined</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Webfleet Solutions, Lytx Create Video-based Solution</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/webfleet-solutions-lytx/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/webfleet-solutions-lytx/</id>
            <category term="Telematics"/>
            <category term="Press Release"/>

        <updated>2021-02-16T21:15:51+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/20/In-Cab.png" alt="Webfleet Solutions Lytx video solution" />
                    Webfleet Solutions is collaborating with Lytx, a global provider of video telematics solutions for fleets, to offer an integrated video-based solution. WEBFLEET Video is a seamless integration of Lytx’s camera&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/20/In-Cab.png" alt="Webfleet Solutions Lytx video solution" />
                <p><strong>Webfleet Solutions is collaborating with Lytx, a global provider of video telematics solutions for fleets, to offer an integrated video-based solution. </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">WEBFLEET Video is a seamless integration of Lytx’s camera technology into Webfleet Solutions’ fleet management system. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Users will be able to access and manage both their vehicles and their in-vehicle cameras via WEBFLEET, the award-winning fleet management platform, which offers a single interface experience. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">WEBFLEET Video combines Webfleet Solutions’ vehicle and driving data with Lytx’s advanced machine vision (MV) and artificial intelligence (AI) powered camera technology to give users the full context of how their fleet is operating on the road. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This gives the user more insight into critical events, helping them to prevent accidents, increase safety for the driver, enhance fleet efficiency and reduce the frequency and cost of insurance claims. </span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Damian Penney, VP of Lytx Europe, explains how Lytx helps protect your time, drivers, and reputation</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DullC5lqzqA" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are excited to combine our expertise to equip many more customers worldwide with best-in-class solutions,” says Damian Penney, vice president, Europe at Lytx. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Many fleet managers today leverage more than one technology, which can be a lot to juggle.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Finding opportunities to consolidate is crucial. Through this integration, customers will be able to seamlessly access industry-leading video-based driver behaviour and fleet management insights,'' Penney adds.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The combination of video and telematics data safeguards drivers and fleets in a number of ways. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, WEBFLEET uses driving behaviour data on things like idling or harsh braking to provide actionable insights and real-time feedback that supports drivers to drive more safely and sustainably. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the addition of Lytx’ video technology, fleet managers now have a better understanding of why these events occur. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">They can protect their drivers from non-fault claims and coach them to achieve a higher level of road safety. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">We are convinced that Lytx, the leading company in video telematics, is the right partner to introduce our fully integrated video solution in WEBFLEET,” says  Raj Bajaj, Vice President Webfleet Solutions International.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Together, we can even better meet the needs of the fleets we serve with increased safety and efficiency. WEBFLEET Video will also provide clear evidence in the event of road traffic incidents.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This protects the driver against fraudulent claims, while also helping the company to avoid lengthy legal proceedings and to refute incorrect damage or injury claims”, Bajaj concludes.</span></p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/null">Telematics Eases Vaccine Rollout</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Actros Fleet The Highlight At Truck Auction</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/actros-fleet-the-highlight-at-truck-auction/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/actros-fleet-the-highlight-at-truck-auction/</id>
            <category term="Truck Auctions"/>

        <updated>2021-03-01T13:41:59+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/19/Truck-auction.JPG" alt="truck auction aerial view" />
                    Park Village Auctions says it has secured a bevvy of quality, bank-repossessed rigid trucks, tractors, and trailers for their latest auction. Stand-out lots for the day include a fleet of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/19/Truck-auction.JPG" alt="truck auction aerial view" />
                <p><strong>Park Village Auctions says it has secured a bevvy of quality, bank-repossessed rigid trucks, tractors, and trailers for their latest auction.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stand-out lots for the day include a fleet of 2018 Mercedes Benz Actros 2645 truck tractors, a 2017 MAN TGM 25-280 rigid, a collection of 2017 GRW tanker trailers, and a Kubota M130 tractor.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The banks have commissioned a great selection of vehicles that offer inviting savings to fleet and logistics managers across the board,” says PVA spokesperson, Natashia Goosen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This auction is not to be missed.”</span></p>
<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://roadtransport.news/mercedes-benz-trucks-retains-lead/">Mercedes-Benz Trucks Retains Heavy-Duty Lead</a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A Scania G460, a MAN TGS 17-374, a UD Quon GW 26-490, an Iveco Stralis 480, a Volvo 420, a Freightliner Argosy and International Pro Sleeper make up the remaining truck tractor stock for the day.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other rigid trucks to be sold include a Powerstar 4035 and a Powerstar 2628 tipper truck, a 2016 FAW 8-140FL and various other models from manufacturers such as Tata, Mercedes-Benz, Hino, Nissan, Mitsubishi, Isuzu and Toyota.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Various Paramount, Henred Fruehauf, Kearny’s, Roadhog, Afrit, SA Truck Bodies and Top Trailers will also be on the block.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hyster forklifts, a Caterpillar 140k Grader and Caterpillar 226B Skidsteer will conclude the sales for the day.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This will be a simulcast auction, which is when we stream the live auction to online participants who bid against people on the floor in real-time,” explains Goosen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The auction will commence at 10:30 am on Thursday, 25 February. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Viewing will be held the day before (Wednesday the 24th) at PVA’s truck yard at gate number 2 of the Nasrec Showgrounds. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Nasrec Showgrounds can be found at Number 1 Nasrec Road, Johannesburg.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Due to Covid-19 safety protocols, the number of people permitted on-site for viewing and attendance at the auction is limited and booking is essential. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For more information, or to register for the auction, visit <a href="https://www.parkvillageauctions.co.za" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.parkvillageauctions.co.za</a> and use web reference 678.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>N4 Upgrade To Be Completed In July</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/n4-upgrade-to-be-completed-in-july/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/n4-upgrade-to-be-completed-in-july/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="National Roads"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:29:21+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The recent rains have wreaked havoc on many of the country’s roads causing millions of rands in damage to road infrastructure. It is noted that poorly maintained roads impact negatively&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>The recent rains have wreaked havoc on many of the country’s roads causing millions of rands in damage to road infrastructure. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is noted that poorly maintained roads impact negatively on communities and the country as a whole.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This highlights the importance of regular maintenance and upgrades which contribute towards keeping the wheels of the economy turning.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bakwena Platinum Corridor Concessionaire (Pty) Ltd (Bakwena) says it places great importance on their road users’ experience of the routes it manages.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Maintenance of road infrastructure assets and sharing updates on the work we are currently engaged in keeps road users informed and prepared,” says Bakwena’s Commercial Manager, Solomon Kganyago.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Bakwena has an ongoing Routine Route Maintenance programme which includes grass cutting, vegetation control, stormwater cleaning, fence/guardrail/signage repairs and pavement defect restoration,” he explains.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our engineers regularly inspect the route to proactively carry out repairs/construction works to maintain the highest standards,” Kganyago adds.</span></p>
<p><strong>Watch: </strong>Recent rains in Mpumalanga claim lives, damage infrastructure</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uyoOH38tqUM" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The current N4 upgrade includes the addition of a 32km second carriageway on the N4 between the M17 and R512 (Brits interchange).  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is a three-year contract which commenced in March 2018. Kganyago says the N4 upgrade is on track and the expected completion date is July 2021.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Further construction works taking place during 2021 include the rehabilitation of the N4 east between Ga-Rankuwa interchange and Doornpoort with an expected commencement date of July 2021.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“These upgrades will improve overall safety and convenience on the route as well as enhance motorists driving experience.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We would like to thank motorists for their patience while we complete these upgrades which are necessary to ensure the N1N4 route meets the highest international standards for motorists,” concludes Kganyago.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
