<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>feed</title>
    <link href="https://roadtransport.news/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://roadtransport.news" />
    <updated>2021-02-19T18:45:37+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://roadtransport.news</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Tata International Africa Introduces Five-year Warranty</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/tata-international-africa-introduces-five-year-warranty/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/tata-international-africa-introduces-five-year-warranty/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="OEM&#x27;s"/>

        <updated>2021-02-19T18:45:37+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Daewoo-Trucks.jpg" alt="Daewoo Trucks warranty" />
                    Tata International Africa has become the first company in Africa to introduce a standard warranty of five years on its entire Medium, Heavy and Extra Heavy Commercial Vehicle range. This&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Daewoo-Trucks.jpg" alt="Daewoo Trucks warranty" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>Tata International Africa has become the first company in Africa to introduce a standard warranty of five years on its entire Medium, Heavy and Extra Heavy Commercial Vehicle range.</strong> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This first-of-its-kind Pan African five-year warranty applies to the full range of Tata Trucks and Buses as well as Daewoo Trucks in all 12 markets in which Tata International Africa operates.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Len Brand, CEO of Tata International Africa says the introduction of a five-year driveline warranty on the commercial vehicle range reinforces the company’s commitment to enhancing the customer ownership experience.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are extremely pleased to offer five-years of assurance on our range of commercial vehicles, while reiterating our commitment to the quality of our products,” says Brand. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Given Africa’s harsh and varied terrains, this new warranty goes a long way towards Tata International Africa’s pursuit of offering enhanced lifecycle benefits to its customers.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“So, whether a customer is in Kenya, Zambia or Ghana, or any other country in which we operate, they will have the same experience and benefits in terms of the warranty.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are customer obsessed and our Uptime strategy is bearing fruit.”</span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Daewoo Trucks in South Africa</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PPG7csCTnms" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Four years ago, we identified the components that we knew were imperative to the growth of our business. The final dream was to be the most sought-after distributor for commercial vehicles in Africa. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have been building towards that, with excellent work on improving the parts and service side of our business.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’ve worked equally hard on our network, expanding our footprint dramatically, especially in South Africa, where we have over 90 touchpoints.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’ve also added new products, working with our OEM partners, to ensure that we are able to provide products for specific niches.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The five-year warranty is applicable to all Tata and Daewoo commercial vehicles first registered on or after 1 January 2021. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is supported across Tata International Africa’s dealership and service network including over 450 touch point outlets and service facilities across the continent.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If a customer needs to sell the vehicle, they will enjoy a higher resale value and the warranty is transferable to the next owner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A warranty of such magnitude gives the customer assurance that the product is robust, reliable and durable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tata International Africa has also been successful in rolling out retail financing arrangements in six African markets.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/Tata-Trucks.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-xs.jpg 300w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-sm.jpg 480w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-md.jpg 768w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/22/responsive/Tata-Trucks-2xl.jpg 1600w"  alt="Tata Trucks warranty" width="800" height="743"></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We started this journey two years ago, and we’re thrilled to offer retail financing to our customers in so many African countries,” Brand continues. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Rest assured, six is not the end of this journey. We are planning to roll this out in all 12 countries in which we operate,” concluded Brand.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tata International Africa operates in South Africa, Ghana, Kenya, Ivory Coast, Malawi, Mozambique Nigeria, Senegal, Tanzania, Uganda, Zambia and Zimbabwe.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Four Causes Of Truck Rollovers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/four-causes-of-truck-rollovers/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/four-causes-of-truck-rollovers/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="Driver Training"/>

        <updated>2021-02-18T17:39:20+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/21/P32.jpg" alt="overturned truck" />
                    Truck rollovers can be devastating. Death or injuries to those involved, damages to property or roads, being responsible for the closure of a road for hours at a time and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/21/P32.jpg" alt="overturned truck" />
                <p><strong>Truck rollovers can be devastating. </strong></p>
<p>Death or injuries to those involved, damages to property or roads, being responsible for the closure of a road for hours at a time and the cost of repairs or replacement and the consequent downtime can leave a company millions out of pocket.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, there is seldom a week that photos of a rollover are not shared in the media.</p>
<p>The managing director of MasterDrive, Eugene Herbert, says with the right conditions a truck rollover happens easily.</p>
<p>“Trucks are prone to these kind of crashes as drivers have to contend with both a high centre of gravity and centrifugal forces that cause the truck to ‘lean’ in a curve or turn."</p>
<p>A number scenarios have high risk of rollovers.</p>
<p>"Four of these are particularly risky for truck drivers yet with the right training drivers can be prepared for what to expect and how to avoid this dangerous and costly position.”</p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Trucks Overturning Compilation</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hz4sNw6nSOg" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 1: Speed and cornering</strong></span></p>
<p>Speed is estimated to be the cause of up to 45% of crashes in corners and on highway onramps and offramps.</p>
<p>“When negotiating a corner, drivers need to use height, load and angle or configuration of the corner to decide what speed is required to safely navigate the corner,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 2: Incorrect loading</strong></span></p>
<p>The high centre of gravity requires the load to be secured. “If the load shifts during cornering the loss of balance increases rollover risk.</p>
<p>"Tankers can also be at increased risk when partially full as the sloshing of the liquid can upset the balance, particularly when cornering,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 3: Abrupt or oversteering </strong></span></p>
<p>Abrupt or sharp steering movements are risky. “The high centre of gravity will cause a truck to roll over if the driver abruptly steers around an obstacle."</p>
<p>"Drivers should also be cautious of oversteering in certain situations, such as when traction decreases."</p>
<p>"When traction is regained but oversteering continues, lateral force increases along with the risk of rollover,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><span style="color: #e50303;"><strong>Scenario 4: Driver error</strong></span></p>
<p>A study by international organisation FMSCA, suggests that 78% of tanker rollovers are due to driver error.</p>
<p>“This can be speeding in bad weather conditions, distracted driving, driving while on medication or while fatigued and various other dangerous driving habits.”</p>
<p>The difficulty with rollovers is that once the truck starts to tip, there is nothing you can do to stop it.</p>
<p>“Additionally, drivers may only feel the start of a rollover when it is well underway. This emphasises the importance of being aware of risk factors and what is required to ensure that you eliminate all the risks you can.</p>
<p>“MasterDrive’s rollover prevention training teaches drivers about risk factors and provides guidance on how to avoid falling victim to one."</p>
<p>"Importantly, the unique engineering of the truck allows drivers to feel what an actual rollover feels like without going all the way over.</p>
<p>"It is an invaluable opportunity to understand a rollover without the financial implications,” says Herbert.</p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="https://roadtransport.news/insurance-and-driver-training-intertwined/">Insurance and driver training intertwined</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Webfleet Solutions, Lytx Create Video-based Solution</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/webfleet-solutions-lytx/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/webfleet-solutions-lytx/</id>
            <category term="Telematics"/>
            <category term="Press Release"/>

        <updated>2021-02-16T21:15:51+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/20/In-Cab.png" alt="Webfleet Solutions Lytx video solution" />
                    Webfleet Solutions is collaborating with Lytx, a global provider of video telematics solutions for fleets, to offer an integrated video-based solution. WEBFLEET Video is a seamless integration of Lytx’s camera&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/20/In-Cab.png" alt="Webfleet Solutions Lytx video solution" />
                <p><strong>Webfleet Solutions is collaborating with Lytx, a global provider of video telematics solutions for fleets, to offer an integrated video-based solution. </strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">WEBFLEET Video is a seamless integration of Lytx’s camera technology into Webfleet Solutions’ fleet management system. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Users will be able to access and manage both their vehicles and their in-vehicle cameras via WEBFLEET, the award-winning fleet management platform, which offers a single interface experience. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">WEBFLEET Video combines Webfleet Solutions’ vehicle and driving data with Lytx’s advanced machine vision (MV) and artificial intelligence (AI) powered camera technology to give users the full context of how their fleet is operating on the road. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This gives the user more insight into critical events, helping them to prevent accidents, increase safety for the driver, enhance fleet efficiency and reduce the frequency and cost of insurance claims. </span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> Damian Penney, VP of Lytx Europe, explains how Lytx helps protect your time, drivers, and reputation</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DullC5lqzqA" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are excited to combine our expertise to equip many more customers worldwide with best-in-class solutions,” says Damian Penney, vice president, Europe at Lytx. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Many fleet managers today leverage more than one technology, which can be a lot to juggle.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Finding opportunities to consolidate is crucial. Through this integration, customers will be able to seamlessly access industry-leading video-based driver behaviour and fleet management insights,'' Penney adds.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The combination of video and telematics data safeguards drivers and fleets in a number of ways. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, WEBFLEET uses driving behaviour data on things like idling or harsh braking to provide actionable insights and real-time feedback that supports drivers to drive more safely and sustainably. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the addition of Lytx’ video technology, fleet managers now have a better understanding of why these events occur. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">They can protect their drivers from non-fault claims and coach them to achieve a higher level of road safety. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">We are convinced that Lytx, the leading company in video telematics, is the right partner to introduce our fully integrated video solution in WEBFLEET,” says  Raj Bajaj, Vice President Webfleet Solutions International.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Together, we can even better meet the needs of the fleets we serve with increased safety and efficiency. WEBFLEET Video will also provide clear evidence in the event of road traffic incidents.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This protects the driver against fraudulent claims, while also helping the company to avoid lengthy legal proceedings and to refute incorrect damage or injury claims”, Bajaj concludes.</span></p>
<p><strong>Now read:</strong> <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/null">Telematics Eases Vaccine Rollout</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Actros Fleet The Highlight At Truck Auction</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/actros-fleet-the-highlight-at-truck-auction/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/actros-fleet-the-highlight-at-truck-auction/</id>
            <category term="Truck Auctions"/>

        <updated>2021-02-15T14:32:56+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/19/Truck-auction.JPG" alt="truck auction aerial view" />
                    Park Village Auctions says it has secured a bevvy of quality, bank-repossessed rigid trucks, tractors, and trailers for their latest auction. Stand-out lots for the day include a fleet of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/19/Truck-auction.JPG" alt="truck auction aerial view" />
                <p><strong>Park Village Auctions says it has secured a bevvy of quality, bank-repossessed rigid trucks, tractors, and trailers for their latest auction.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stand-out lots for the day include a fleet of 2018 Mercedes Benz Actros 2645 truck tractors, a 2017 MAN TGM 25-280 rigid, a collection of 2017 GRW tanker trailers, and a Kubota M130 tractor.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The banks have commissioned a great selection of vehicles that offer inviting savings to fleet and logistics managers across the board,” says PVA spokesperson, Natashia Goosen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This auction is not to be missed.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A Scania G460, a MAN TGS 17-374, a UD Quon GW 26-490, an Iveco Stralis 480, a Volvo 420, a Freightliner Argosy and International Pro Sleeper make up the remaining truck tractor stock for the day.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other rigid trucks to be sold include a Powerstar 4035 and a Powerstar 2628 tipper truck, a 2016 FAW 8-140FL and various other models from manufacturers such as Tata, Mercedes-Benz, Hino, Nissan, Mitsubishi, Isuzu and Toyota.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Various Paramount, Henred Fruehauf, Kearny’s, Roadhog, Afrit, SA Truck Bodies and Top Trailers will also be on the block.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hyster forklifts, a Caterpillar 140k Grader and Caterpillar 226B Skidsteer will conclude the sales for the day.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This will be a simulcast auction, which is when we stream the live auction to online participants who bid against people on the floor in real-time,” explains Goosen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The auction will commence at 10:30 am on Thursday, 25 February. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Viewing will be held the day before (Wednesday the 24th) at PVA’s truck yard at gate number 2 of the Nasrec Showgrounds. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Nasrec Showgrounds can be found at Number 1 Nasrec Road, Johannesburg.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Due to Covid-19 safety protocols, the number of people permitted on-site for viewing and attendance at the auction is limited and booking is essential. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For more information, or to register for the auction, visit <a href="https://www.parkvillageauctions.co.za" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.parkvillageauctions.co.za</a> and use web reference 678.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>N4 Upgrade To Be Completed In July</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/n4-upgrade-to-be-completed-in-july/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/n4-upgrade-to-be-completed-in-july/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="National Roads"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:29:21+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The recent rains have wreaked havoc on many of the country’s roads causing millions of rands in damage to road infrastructure. It is noted that poorly maintained roads impact negatively&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>The recent rains have wreaked havoc on many of the country’s roads causing millions of rands in damage to road infrastructure. </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is noted that poorly maintained roads impact negatively on communities and the country as a whole.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This highlights the importance of regular maintenance and upgrades which contribute towards keeping the wheels of the economy turning.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bakwena Platinum Corridor Concessionaire (Pty) Ltd (Bakwena) says it places great importance on their road users’ experience of the routes it manages.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Maintenance of road infrastructure assets and sharing updates on the work we are currently engaged in keeps road users informed and prepared,” says Bakwena’s Commercial Manager, Solomon Kganyago.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Bakwena has an ongoing Routine Route Maintenance programme which includes grass cutting, vegetation control, stormwater cleaning, fence/guardrail/signage repairs and pavement defect restoration,” he explains.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our engineers regularly inspect the route to proactively carry out repairs/construction works to maintain the highest standards,” Kganyago adds.</span></p>
<p><strong>Watch: </strong>Recent rains in Mpumalanga claim lives, damage infrastructure</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uyoOH38tqUM" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The current N4 upgrade includes the addition of a 32km second carriageway on the N4 between the M17 and R512 (Brits interchange).  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is a three-year contract which commenced in March 2018. Kganyago says the N4 upgrade is on track and the expected completion date is July 2021.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Further construction works taking place during 2021 include the rehabilitation of the N4 east between Ga-Rankuwa interchange and Doornpoort with an expected commencement date of July 2021.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“These upgrades will improve overall safety and convenience on the route as well as enhance motorists driving experience.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We would like to thank motorists for their patience while we complete these upgrades which are necessary to ensure the N1N4 route meets the highest international standards for motorists,” concludes Kganyago.</span></p>
<p><br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Insurance and driver training intertwined</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/insurance-and-driver-training-intertwined/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/insurance-and-driver-training-intertwined/</id>
            <category term="Opinion"/>
            <category term="Driver Training"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:33:17+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/17/driver-training.jpg" alt="driver training" />
                    For many drivers the prospect of a lower insurance premium might be very appealing, especially as many households recover from the economic difficulty that resulted from lockdown. One way in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/17/driver-training.jpg" alt="driver training" />
                <p><strong>For many drivers the prospect of a lower insurance premium might be very appealing, especially as many households recover from the economic difficulty that resulted from lockdown. </strong></p>
<p>One way in which to do this, is through driver training.</p>
<p>The managing director of MasterDrive, Eugene Herbert, recommends that all drivers contact their insurance providers about their driver training policies.</p>
<p>“As driver training can drastically reduce your chances of being involved in a crash, many insurers encourage clients to undertake driver training and reduce monthly premiums in return."</p>
<p>"Drivers win with a saving on insurance costs and insurers benefit by avoiding the considerably larger costs that come with a crash."</p>
<p>“These discounts can take various forms and percentages depending on the insurer. It is possible that some insurers offer discounts to certain groups, such as those falling into particular age groups, as they have a higher risk of crashes."</p>
<p>"Whatever the case is with your insurer, it is worthwhile finding out what value the insurer places on a driving course and how this can benefit you financially.”</p>
<p><strong>Watch: </strong>15 Defensive Driving Secrets That Can Save Your Life</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UnqOmbR2qNs" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Some insurers do not offer discounted premiums in exchange for driver training but this does not mean that there is no benefit for drivers.</p>
<p>“Besides the general advantages of driver training, your chance of crashing is drastically reduced, meaning you also get to avoid costly excess payments if you are in an accident.</p>
<p>“Excess can easily be equal to a good portion of your salary or savings, making even the smallest of crashes a costly endeavour."</p>
<p>"This is not to mention the costs that come from damages to other cars or property and medical expenses associated with accidents.”</p>
<p>For business owners, the savings could be massive. “Companies are often offered the same benefits that the individual driver is.</p>
<p>"If driver training becomes part of company policy, the savings extend past a monthly discount but will also result in a reduction in fleet costs, damage to your public image and costly downtime.</p>
<p>“Even companies that are self-insured will find a welcome relief from the demands on their insurance budget."</p>
<p>"When viewed from this perspective, driver training should be seen as something that is as important as maintenance or insurance itself.”</p>
<p>Whatever options are available to you, there are benefits.</p>
<p>“Insurance and driver training should be viewed as a whole. One without the other can result in additional and unnecessary expenses,” says Herbert.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Advertise on Road Transport News</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/advertise-on-road-transport-news/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/advertise-on-road-transport-news/</id>

        <updated>2021-02-10T10:14:58+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A number of advertising opportunities are available, including website banners, sponsorships and advertorials. Use the website to reach a highly targeted group of readers and decision makers interested in road&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>A number of advertising opportunities are available, including website banners, sponsorships and advertorials. </p>
<p>Use the website to reach a highly targeted group of readers and decision makers interested in road transport, logistics and trucking in South Africa.</p>
<p>Please <a href="https://roadtransport.news/contact/">contact us</a> for advertising rates and options.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Stop AARTO Now - Road Freight Association</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/stop-aarto-now-road-freight-association/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/stop-aarto-now-road-freight-association/</id>
            <category term="Press Release"/>
            <category term="AARTO"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:29:37+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/15/RFA-slams-AARTO.jpg" alt="AARTO slammed by RFA" />
                    The Road Freight Association (RFA) is shocked and deeply concerned about the recent suspension of the Road Traffic Infringement Agency’s Chief Executive Officer, Japh Chuwe, amidst allegations of “serious maladministration”&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/15/RFA-slams-AARTO.jpg" alt="AARTO slammed by RFA" />
                <p><strong><a href="http://rfa.co.za/RFA/index.php/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Road Freight Association </a>(RFA) is shocked and deeply concerned about the recent suspension of the Road Traffic Infringement Agency’s Chief Executive Officer, Japh Chuwe, amidst allegations of “serious maladministration” by the Auditor-General. </strong></p>
<p>This has a severe impact on the implementation of the highly controversial <a href="http://www.rtia.co.za/ruploads/administrative_adjudication_of_road_traffic_offences_act_1998-661.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Administrative Adjudication of Road Traffic Offences Act </a>(AARTO), which is scheduled to be implemented in July this year.<br><br>Whilst we welcome the uncovering of corruption, it would be irresponsible and reckless for Government to proceed with the implementation of AARTO.</p>
<p>The RFA has over the years expressed concern and uneasiness about AARTO and its susceptibility to fraud, corruption, and money laundering.</p>
<p>The RTIA’s latest announcement is confirmation of our worst fears. <br><br>Once AARTO is implemented, the <a href="http://www.rtia.co.za/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RTIA</a> will be handling Billions of Rand. How can we now trust the entity – especially when the dishonesty and corruption is allegedly at the highest level in the Agency?</p>
<p>We already face huge corruption, extortion and intimidation at the hands of traffic police on a daily basis and this latest development has highlighted how rampant dishonesty is in the public service – especially in the traffic law enforcement and management structures.</p>
<p>These allegations have undermined what little faith we had in RTIA. If the system is implemented, we envisage theft on a grand scale. </p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> <span class="style-scope yt-formatted-string" dir="auto">The latest draft of AARTO regulations has been gazetted by the Transport Department.</span></p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cm_z8u75dJc" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>The RFA once again proposes that AARTO be shelved. The continuously amended system is all about generating revenue and not at all about road safety, which was what the system was originally about.</p>
<p>Huge administrative resources will be required to implement and sustain an antiquated and cumbersome system, putting additional burdens on already-overburdened government authorities and the private sector.<br><br>The <a href="https://www.rtmc.co.za/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Road Traffic Management Corporation </a>(RTMC) – another Agency of the Department of Transport – already costs motorists hundreds of millions of Rand per annum through the levy imposed on all <a href="http://www.enatis.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">eNatis </a>transactions.</p>
<p>This was supposed to be a temporary measure to get the RTMC on its feet. Like all other levies,  this has become permanent with no added value to citizens.</p>
<p>The RTMC needs to step up and do its job, that is, manage road traffic according to proper traffic management strategies with effective centralised road safety interventions and operational management.<br><br>The RFA believes that proper traffic management strategies which focus resources to address hazardous locations and other aspects of unsafe road behaviour would be far more effective in improving road safety – rather than the current cumbersome AARTO system being proposed.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>More MB Truck Models Get Fleetboard </title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/more-mb-truck-models-get-fleetboard/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/more-mb-truck-models-get-fleetboard/</id>
            <category term="Telematics"/>
            <category term="Press Release"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:29:47+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/14/MB-Trucks-Fleetboard.jpg" alt="Mercedes-Benz Fleetboard" />
                    Fleetboard from Mercedes-Benz Trucks is now part of the package for the Actros and selected Arocs distribution models. Fleetboard has been offered on the Actros range since 2009 and is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/14/MB-Trucks-Fleetboard.jpg" alt="Mercedes-Benz Fleetboard" />
                <p><strong><a href="https://www.fleetboard.info/#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fleetboard</a> from Mercedes-Benz Trucks is now part of the package for the Actros and selected Arocs distribution models.</strong></p>
<p>Fleetboard has been offered on the Actros range since 2009 and is today not only available as a serial standard on the selected Mercedes-Benz Trucks models, it is also available for other vehicle makes as well.<br><br>Efficiency is the sum of the details; Fleetboard is geared to take RoadEfficiency to the next level through its unique service offerings to ensure lower total cost, greater safety and maximised use for customers.</p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> How does Fleetboard work?</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ph-3whc2rNE" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p>Available in South Africa for many years, the Fleetboard system has established itself as a leading telematics solution for Mercedes-Benz Truck customers.</p>
<p><strong>Related: <span style="color: #e50303;"><a href="https://roadtransport.news/telematics-eases-vaccine-rollout/" style="color: #e50303;">Telematics Eases Vaccine Rollout</a></span></strong><a href="https://roadtransport.news/telematics-eases-vaccine-rollout/"></a></p>
<p>Boasting multiple benefits such as performance analysis and reports for vehicles and drivers, mapping and trip records including accurate fuel consumption, service and maintenance management as well as expert training and analysis.<br><br><a href="https://www.mercedes-benz-trucks.com/en_ZA/home.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mercedes-Benz Trucks Southern Africa</a> understands that managing a fleet can be stressful and hard to keep up with, and believes that this strategic decision will be beneficial to customers within the long-haul and distribution segment.</p>
<p>Effective utilisation of the system within these industries means that the truck can go further for longer, contributing to added savings in the long-run.<br><br>This is a significant step for the brand that is set to substantially benefit fleet owners and their respective drivers, as they efficiently run their fleet across Southern Africa.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Telematics Eases Vaccine Rollout</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tristan Wiggill</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://roadtransport.news/telematics-eases-vaccine-rollout/"/>
        <id>https://roadtransport.news/telematics-eases-vaccine-rollout/</id>
            <category term="Telematics"/>
            <category term="Press Release"/>

        <updated>2021-02-14T18:30:11+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/13/Vaccine-distribution-logistics.jpg" alt="Vaccine logistics and distribution" />
                    President Cyril Ramaphosa has described the rollout of the COVID-19 vaccine as “the largest and most complex logistical undertaking in SA’s history”. Acquiring the vaccine is only the start of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://roadtransport.news/media/posts/13/Vaccine-distribution-logistics.jpg" alt="Vaccine logistics and distribution" />
                <p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">President Cyril Ramaphosa has described the rollout of the COVID-19 vaccine as “the largest and most complex logistical undertaking in SA’s history”. </span></span></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">Acquiring the vaccine is only the start of SA achieving its target of group immunity – the vaccine still needs to be distributed safely. </span></span></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">That means maintaining it at the right temperature throughout the transportation process, and tracking distribution trucks to ensure product integrity and avoid tampering or theft. </span></span></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">“Not only are we transporting small glass vials to every corner of our country, we must also maintain these doses at below freezer temperatures the entire trip," says <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/justin-manson-b5019216/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Justin Manson</a>, Sales Director at <a href="https://www.webfleet.com/en_gb/webfleet/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Webfleet Solutions</a>.</span></span></p>
<p><strong>Related: <span style="color: #e50303;"><a href="https://roadtransport.news/serco-gets-frosty-with-sequence-logistics/" style="color: #e50303;">Serco Gets Frosty With Sequence Logistics</a></span></strong></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">“Government must work with fleet management companies to develop a network of real-time tracking systems that measure, record and transmit trip details to ensure vaccines are transported to even the most remote parts of the country as safely and efficiently as possible.”</span></span></p>
<p><strong>Watch:</strong> What is asset tracking?</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="449" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W8jnsoTewQw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">Tracking and monitoring systems form a vital part of the vaccine transportation process in SA. </span></span></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">They provide fleet managers with a real-time view of the distribution trucks, including the correct functioning of refrigerated trailers, vehicle maintenance requirements and usage, driving behaviour, and the ability to detect theft in time to take effective action.</span></span></p>
<p><strong>Worth reading: <span style="color: #e50303;"><a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/null" style="color: #e50303;">How to get a cold chain edge</a></span></strong></p>
<p class="paragraph"><span class="normaltextrun"><span lang="EN-GB">“Solutions like Asset Tracking offer advanced capabilities for better control of the total vaccine transportation value chain for enhanced efficiency and safety, while significantly reducing human error,” adds Manson.</span></span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
